<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section anchor="authentication" title="Authentication">
  <t>Currently, authentication is done, using a SASL mechanism.
  Which mechanisms are supported can be discovered using the INFO request.
  The PLAIN authentication mechanism SHOULD be supported by any implementation.
  </t>
  <t>As encryption of the transport protocol is mandatory in production use of FOSP, the SASL security layer is not used.
  </t>
  <section anchor="auth-anonymous" title="Anonymous">
    <t>A client may sent request without being authenticated.
    All requests are then assumed to be performed by an anonymous user.
    </t>
    <t>However, once the client started authentication, it SHOULD NOT sent any request except for those needed for the authentication.
    All requests that are sent before successfully completing the authentication MUST still be performed as anonymous user.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="auth-sasl" title="SASL">
    <t>The service name specified by this protocol's profile is "fosp".
    </t>
    <t>To initiate authentication and to exchange SASL messages, the AUTH request is used.
    Depending on the mechanism, multiple requests might be needed to successfully authenticate.
    In this case the server MUST respond with a not final response code in the range of 3xx.
    The SASL messages are transported as JSON objects in the bodies of the requests and responses.
    All SASL message objects consist of an object with a "sasl" field.
    This field contains an object with the actual SASL message.
    </t>
    <t>The authentication is initiated by the client with a AUTH request.
    The SASL object in the body MUST contain a field called "mechanism" that specifies the SASL mechanism to be used.
    Furthermore, it MUST contain a field called "authorization-identity" that contains the fully qualified user name of the user that should be authenticated.
    Optionally, the object CAN contain a field called "initial-response", containing the initial response of the client, if the mechanism specifies one.
    The initial response MUST be BASE64 encoded.
    An empty initial response is indicated by an empty string, while no initial response is indicated by the absence of the "initial-response" field.
    </t>
    <t>Depending on the mechanism and the previously exchanged messages, the server can either respond with a challenge or an authentication outcome.
    If a challenge is returned by the server, it MUST be returned with a status code 310.
    The body of the response then contains a SASL object with a "challenge" field that contains the challenge in BASE64 encoding.
    If an authentication outcome is returned, it MUST be returned with a status code 200 on success or with a status code 401 on failure.
    The body of this response contains a SASL object with a "outcome" field that contains the outcome in BASE64 encoding.
    Additional data can be provided, BASE64 encoded, in the "additional-data" field.
    If there is additional data but it is empty, then the field MUST be the empty string.
    Otherwise, if there is no additional data, the field MUST NOT be present.
    </t>
    <t>If the server does return a challenge with a 310 status code, the client will sent a new AUTH request.
    The new request contains a SASL object with the "response" field, containing the SASL response, BASE64 encoded.
    </t>
    <t>Once the authentication was completed successfully, all further requests are processed in the name of the authenticated user.
    A second authentication SHOULD not be attempted on the same connection/session and a server MAY reject all further AUTH requests.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
